hey this is Bret Urus uh here to teach
you about some different core stability
stuff you can do with the foam roller um
Les you've been living in a cave for the
last decade you've seen one of these
foam rollers um people use it for self
myofascial release um for soft tissue
quality soft tissue Health um but I'm
going to show you a different way you
can use it for core stability and it's
kind of funny because I don't know why
I've never film this video because um I
wrote it about it in my my glute ebook
like two years ago and uh I tested the
EMG activity of these exercis they get
you a lot higher activation than um then
closed chain bridging things do um these
like like planks and and uh front planks
and and side planks and things like that
the these exercises are amazing and I
for some reason I've just never showed
them to people what's ironic is that
um I learned this from a chiropractor
like 8 to 10 years ago I at the time art
Active Release techniques was becoming
popular so I found an art um
practitioner and he showed these to me
and it's funny because I bought a foam
roller from him and I don't think I've
ever seen anyone in the fitness industry
talk about this obviously he learned it
from someone so um there are people
promoting it but I've just never seen
you know anyone in the online um circles
that I go through talk about these
exercis but um I'll just kind of run
through and show you the different
exercises but probably the best one um
is the one I'll show you right now but
what I love about this is you can train
course stability is Vector specific so
you can be strong in one vector and weak
in another like a lot of people may have
strong Erectors and and you know they
have good you know anti flection
stability but they don't have good
rotary stability so um
this can be used to train all the
different vectors so I'll just kind of
roll through and show you how to do
these but the first one this one is
called a uh prone or sorry a supine
torso hold so supine right facing
upwards prone is facing down so supine
I'm facing upwards and I'm going to hold
my torso off the foam roller so um I get
start here and then I'm going to roll my
torso up and just hold my spine in
neutral so I roll to here get about
right here get low on and now I'm just
holding my spine as you can see I start
shaking like crazy I'm already like I
don't know if you can tell but I'm
totally trembling all right I can't hold
it much longer but if I want to make it
easier put your arms here or roll down a
little bit make it harder roll to the
edge you can put your arms here to make
it a little bit harder or you could go
overhead like that you could even hold
on the weight if you wanted but this is
crazy hard
um kills me every time I do it so um and
if you weigh a lot like me my torso is
pretty big it's long and and and weighs
a lot so this just crushes my my uh my
core and my abdominals okay so that's a
supine torso hold you can also do a
supine uh leg hold which is kind of this
just like that but I'm holding my legs
instead I'm just going to kind of
go like
that and I just hold for time try to get
my body in a straight
line okay that one works the lower abs a
little bit more um a lot of people will
say that you can't isolate the upper and
lower abs but you can I have about 10
studies to to prove it um or to show
evidence for that and I also found the
same thing in my own
um experiments that I did with the upper
and lower rectus abdominis so that's
going to work the lower rectus more um
but the the the Torso one is the better
of the two it's just amazing Try It
You'll see okay now I'm going to go for
rotary stuff so this is an amazing
exercise right here I just get I get in
the middle okay so my back the the fo
roll is running up and down my spine now
I'm just going to roll as far out as I
can can I'm pretty strong in this so I'm
going to go all the way out to my middle
arm and I keep my core straight okay
keep my spine straight so
there all right now next side
okay what I like about that it works the
glute really well with the oblique okay
so you can also do that prone so that
was a supine rotary hold this would be a
prone rotary hold and you just kind of
just kind of go like
this and hold it there and then the
other
side is good
there okay
so um we went through the supine
variations we went through the rotary
variations now I'm going to show you the
side
variations all
right here I just from
here okay that's a a side torso hold all
right and I would do the other side
right you can kind of adjust it to get
more activity by kind of sliding up and
down more okay so you can also if you
wanted you could kind of do it this way
and just have your legs straight out
roll it down a little more make it
harder okay yeah right there
okay next
side so this would be a side leg hold
right okay and then last one would be
the prone variations which would work
more of the posterior chain and you
could have a prone torso hold and for
this one just keep everything in neutral
and just squeeze the glutes see my
glutes okay Boom turn the glutes on and
just hold
here and then you could do now I'm
holding my torso up you could also do
this and hold the legs up kind of here
it's too easy I roll down more increase
the lever so now now it's harder and
then you can also kind of do like what
what's dangerous about a Superman from
the ground is you're hyperextended but
you can kind of do it this way squeeze
the glutes and just kind of hover and
not hyper ex
then you'll find it works the the
posterior chain really well
so um we trained core stability through
all the different vectors we did did
supine supine
torso supine
rotary we did a s side line or sorry we
did rotary we did um Pro uh supine
rotary and prone rotary we did Sid
lineing torso s side lineing lower body
and then we did prone uh torso and prone
lower body and can kind of like a prone
um up torso and lower body so lot of
different variations but definitely the
best one by far is the supine torso hold
again try it just start here roll back
hold it right here if you're like me
you'll just start shaking like
crazy amazing exercise so
anyway give it a try I think you'll like
the different core stability exercises
it's great for variation um a lot of
people have been doing planks and side
planks and Poff presses for a long time
now and are kind of looking for some
variety but what's cool is if you have
one of these at home you know you can do
this kind of after you do some foam
rolling do some stability work so all
right hope you like the video take care